Guide to the ILGWU Records, 1884-2006, bulk 1923-1995.
ILGWU Records, 1884-2006, bulk 1923-1995.
The records of the Education Department and the Legal Department are larger than other department records in this series. In addition to seeing how individual staff went about their work in the Education Department, the collection of department publications (5780/166) spans seventy-five years of the union’s history and includes not only writings and speeches by Fannia Cohn and Mark Starr, but also department publications for union members and catalogues of other publications available to members through the department, both documenting the kinds of lessons the ILGWU staff thought worthwhile to teach. The records of the Legal Department document major legal cases with garment manufacturers, such as Kellwood and Judy Bond, in court documents and leaflets, as well as address legal issues relating to the ownership and maintenance of ILGWU institutions such as the Union Health Center and Unity House. The controversy over the right of union organizers to organize themselves is also documented in the records of the ILGWU’s Legal Department.
Researchers should note that over the course of the ILGWU’s nearly century-long history, many departments and projects were formed and disbanded, and a good number of these are not represented in this series. Thorough review of the ILGWU’s Convention Report and Proceedings will yield information on departments’ formation, activities, and dissolution. Reports to the General Executive Board between international conventions will also provide basic information on the activities of departments and institutions. The general collection of ILGWU publications (5780 PUBS) contains newsletters, pamphlets and other printed material that supplement the department publications found in this collection.
Beyond published and other printed material, information on departments and institutions may be found in the papers of ILGWU presidents, other officers, and staff. These individuals sometimes worked in or directed departments before moving into administrative positions. The papers of Executive Vice-President Wilbur Daniels may contain material of interest, for example, since Daniels worked in the Legal Department, Research Department, and Master Agreements Department over the course of his long career in the ILGWU. Likewise, researchers interested in the work of the Political-Education Department should review Assistant Vice President Gus Tyler’s papers.
SERIES VIII. PRINTED MATERIAL, 1910-1995
The collections organized in this series form the core of printed material in the ILGWU Records and consist of printed materials either collected or published by the ILGWU and its affiliates. This includes the official organs of the ILGWU, namely The Ladies’ Garment Worker and Justice, and publications from some of its affiliates. In addition to periodical publications of the union, this series contains publications by union officers, printed material collected by union officers and departments, and publications of entities of which the ILGWU had a vested interest.
Only for the purposes of description, this scope and content note and the detailed listings below are divided into two: Official Organs of the ILGWU, and Other Printed Material. This is a somewhat false distinction, given that the largest of the collections in this series, 5780 PUBS, contains every kind of aforementioned publication. Thus, if a particular title, or a particular issue of a title, is not found in the collection first consulted, researchers should be sure to consult 5780 PUBS and, if possible, all of the collections comprising this series as well as collections of publications in other series.
Official Organs of the ILGWU
The Ladies’ Garment Worker was the first official organ of the ILGWU. First published by the ILGWU in April 1910, the paper was issued monthly in Yiddish, English, and Italian. The Ladies’ Garment Worker included reports on activities of the ILGWU and its affiliates, analysis of the garment industry, articles by officers of the union, reports of union activities, and announcements of upcoming events. Two features of The Ladies’ Garment Worker are especially useful for basic reference regarding the ILGWU’s growth in membership and changes in leadership: the publication regularly included directories of local unions’ number, name, and mailing address, as well as a listing of general officers’ names, titles, and addresses.
At the end of 1918, The Ladies’ Garment Worker ceased publication, and in 1919, Justice became the official organ of the ILGWU. It remained the official newspaper of the International until the ILGWU’s merger with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995. In addition to continuing to publish Yiddish, English, and Italian editions, the ILGWU also published a Spanish edition. The paper was published monthly, except in the summer (July-August) when it was published bimonthly. As with its predecessor publication, Justice featured articles about union activities, analysis of the garment industry, announcements of upcoming events, and communications from ILGWU officers. Sometimes, it included information on local union elections, notice of television programs featuring the ILGWU, and photographs of members and officers. These photographs, along with the illustration work of Bernard Seaman and others, made Justice more visually-striking than the former ILGWU newspaper.
Other Printed Material
The materials published or collected by the International and its affiliates document the activities of the ILGWU’s members, staff, and officers. The official organs of local unions, district councils, and regional departments are included in this series. Writings by ILGWU officers include Yetta Horn’s translation of Abraham Rosenberg’s Memoirs of a Cloakmaker and unpublished union histories by Fannia Cohn, Sol Goldberg, Julius Hochman, and others. Charles Zimmerman’s collection of pamphlets covers a wide range of sources, from the AFL-CIO’s Free Trade Union Committee to Roy Wilson Howard’s interview with Joseph Stalin. Garment trade publications, including bulletins and newspapers, are also included.
While the collections in this series constitute the bulk of printed material in the ILGWU records, researchers should also consult collections of printed materials that are listed as part of other series. In most instances, these collections are the result of transferring printed materials from a collection of archival records, e.g. 5780/059 consists of records of Local 23-25, and 5780/059 PUBS consists of publications of or collected by Local 23-25. In other instances, such as with the Auditing Department records, the printed materials constitute the entirety of the records for that affiliate. Descriptions and listings for these collections may be found in Series I. Constitutions, By-Laws and Conventions, Series III. Locals, and Series VII. Departments and Institutions.
SERIES IX. PHOTOGRAPHS AND AUDIO-VISUAL, 1885-1995
This series contains the core collections of visual materials of the ILGWU Records, including photographs, photographic negatives, film and video, audio recordings, broadside, ad boards, and exhibit displays. Photographic and audio-visual materials collections associated with an individual or specific ILGWU affiliate are included in other series. These collections of media are indicated by their title names, as well as by “AV” and “P” appended to their collection numbers.
The collections that comprise this series include materials that came to the archives in a number of ways. They were created for publication, circulated for internal use, commissioned to professional photographers and filmmakers, collected by staff and members, and purchased from other unions. Given this, these collections provide a kind of holistic picture of the union, documenting how the ILGWU managed its public image, communicated with members, and learned from other labor organizations.
For example, the photographs collected for possible publication in Justice (5780/102 P) include familiar images that made it into print in the ILGWU’s official organ, while posters and fliers from the collection of broadsides (5780/109) might have been posted in a certain city or only distributed to workers in a particular shop. Likewise, the audio-visual, film, and photograph collections (5780 AV, 5780 F, and 5780 P), contain materials that were likely to be heard or viewed only by members of a local union, such as the audio taped proceedings of a meeting or a home movie of a trip to Unity House. These collections also contain materials that were to be broadcast nationally, such as interviews with ILGWU officers or Union Label commercials. An oral history project by the staff of the ILGWU Archives resulted in the core holdings of audio recordings (5780 OH) and transcripts (5780/110 OHT) of oral history interviews with ILGWU officers and staff.
The visual materials contained in this series are complemented by the records housed elsewhere in the collection. The reports and proceedings of the ILGWU’s conventions can help to identify individuals in unlabeled photographs of committees and local union delegations. The organizing efforts detailed in the records of a regional department were sometimes photographed from meeting to rally to press conference. The negotiations and conflicts over the establishment of piece rates complement the time and motion studies conducted by the ILGWU’s Management-Engineering Department. Researchers would do well to review materials in other series of the ILGWU Records.
SERIES X. SCRAPBOOKS AND MEMORABILIA, 1910-1995
This series is comprised of 10 collections of scrapbooks and memorabilia created or collected by ILGWU members, officers, and staff. Taken together, they document the ILGWU’s work for its members, as well as the union’s broad and varied approach to maintaining a place in the broader public’s eye. The international union banners, district council charters, local strike placards, and individual staff members’ awards made the union highly visible to the considerable ILGWU membership and the public at-large. The wide range of ILGWU and Union Label merchandise available to members and industry representatives, the sponsorship of a women’s apparel design award, and articles in the trade press kept the ILGWU emblem visible to a wide public.
Two collections—one of union banners, one of union memorabilia—constitute the bulk of this series. The collection of union banners includes those used by the international, local unions, and allied organizations that were at union and public events. The collection of union memorabilia contains souvenirs from the international conventions, merchandise featuring the ILGWU seal, Union Label Department promotional material, awards, certificates, and citations for individuals, charters for ILGWU affiliates, and placards from pickets, rallies, and other labor actions.
Several collections of memorabilia relate specifically to staff and officers of the ILGWU. David Dubinsky’s collection of memorabilia is the largest of these, but Kitty Goldstein, Murray Gross, and Myrtle Banks also collected ILGWU memorabilia. While these include materials that might also be found in the general memorabilia collections—such as Union Label fabrics, ILGWU merchandise, and souvenirs from the union’s international conventions—they are distinguished by the awards and citations presented to the individuals from social and political organizations. The collection relating to the case against Benedict Macri, who was charged in the murder of union organizer William Lurye, is focused on a staff member of the ILGWU, albeit in a different light.
Other collections relate to social, cultural, and political organizations with which the ILGWU was closely related. These include entities owned by the ILGWU, such as the Poconos vacation resort Unity House and the New York City radio station WFDR-FM, as well as the American Labor Party, with which the ILGWU was closely involved since the political party’s formation in 1936. This series also includes collections that document the ILGWU’s important role in the women’s apparel industry. These include scrapbooks of news clippings from Women’s Wear Daily, and scrapbooks on the ILGWU-sponsored fashion prize, America’s Next Great Designer Award.
Records in other series complement these memorabilia collections. Photographs of ILGWU members—attending the international convention, picketing a local shop, or attending a national rally—sometimes include images of some of the placards, signs, clothing and accessories held in these collections. Textual and photographic records of the ILGWU’s conventions help to date and put into context convention souvenirs. Likewise, reports from the Union Label Department recount campaigns to promote the label within the industry and to the general public, and film and television productions from the department underscore the scale of the campaign. The papers of David Dubinsky are especially complementary of the memorabilia on WFDR-FM, Unity House, and the ILGWU’s involvement with the American Labor Party.
SERIES XI. MISCELLANY, 1895-1992
This series consists of two small collections of miscellaneous records of the ILGWU. 5780/061 consists primarily of records from the Research Department, but other records in the collection suggest that the Research Department may not have been the affiliate that originally transferred the records. Collection 5780/200 consists primarily of publications, but other, a few non-published materials are included as well.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Sigman, Morris.; Schlesinger, Benjamin, 1876-1932.; Dubinsky, David, 1892-; Stulberg, Louis.; Chaikin, Sol.; Antonini, Luigi, 1883-1968.; Zimmerman, Charles S., 1896-1983.; Pesotta, Rose, 1896-; Cohn, Fannia Mary, 1885-1962.; Nagler, Isidore, 1895-; Tyler, Gus.; Stein, Leon, 1912-; Mazur, Jay.; Daniels, Wilbur.; Solomon, Irwin.; Howard, Alan.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Unity House.; American Federation of Labor. Committee for Industrial Organization.; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.); Democratic Party (N.Y.); Liberal Party of New York State.
Subjects:
Trade-unions -- Clothing workers -- United States -- History.; Trade-unions -- Clothing workers -- New York (State) -- New York -- History.; Clothing workers -- United States -- History.; Clothing workers -- New York (State) -- New York -- History.; Clothing trade -- United States -- History.; Clothing trade -- New York (State) -- New York -- History.; Jews -- Employment -- United States -- History.; Jews -- Employment -- New York (State) -- New York -- History.; Italian Americans -- Employment -- United States -- History.; Italian Americans -- Employment -- New York (State) -- New York -- History.; Afro-Americans -- Employment -- History.; Afro-Americans -- Employment -- New York (State) -- New York -- History.; Trade-union health centers -- United States.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Provenance:
In 1973, the records of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union (ILGWU) were initially assembled as the ILGWU Archives by Vice President and General Manager of the New York Cloak Joint Board Henoch Mendelsund, and in large part, processed and maintained by ILGWU Archivist Robert Lazar, Ethel Goldwasser, and other union staff until the ILGWU Archives’ closure in 1987. That year, President Jay Mazur arranged for the transfer of the ILGWU records from the ILGWU Archives at the union’s international headquarters in New York City to the Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives at Cornell University’s Ithaca campus. Beginning with this first transfer of records in 1987 until the ILGWU’s merger with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) in 1995, the ILGWU regularly sent its non-active records to the Kheel Center, resulting in a substantial and varied body of material. Since 1995, additional ILGWU materials have periodically been sent to the Kheel Center from UNITE and UNITE-HERE. These records, totaling more than 2,000 linear feet, document the rich and complex history of the ILGWU and the garment industry in the United States.
In 2010, the ILGWU 21st Century Heritage Fund provided a 2-year grant to continue the processing of the ILGWU records.
RELATED MATERIAL
5243. Mark Starr Papers, 1951.
5244. George Moses Price Files and Scrapbook.
5430 mf. Morris Hillquit Papers on Microfilm.
5459. Serafino Romualdi Papers.
5508m. Hilda Hubert Tanner Papers.
5783 P. Historical Garment Workers Photographs from Socialist Call.
5836 mf. ILGWU Joint Board of Locals of Needles Trades Workers Industrial Union Minute Book on Microfilm.
5864. ILGWU Chicago Joint Board Additional.
5909m. Mark Starr "An Adventure in Education" Manuscript.
5928. Elaine Leeder Collection of Rose Pesotta Papers.
5928 AV. Rose Pesotta Audio-Visual Materials.
5928 P. Rose Pesotta Photographs.
5983m. UNITE Convention Document.
5998 mf. Fannia Cohn Papers on Microfilm.
6036/001. Elias Lieberman Manuscripts.
6036/002. YIVO Archives Interviews in "Amerikaner Yiddishe Geschiente Bel-Pe".
6036/003. YIVO Project Interviews in the Irving Howe Collection conducted by Bernard Rosenberg.
6036/004. ILGWU 75th Anniversary Proclamation from a variety of sources.
6036/005. Louis Levine "Women's Garment Workers" Manuscript.
6036/006. Harry M. Goldman "Pins and Needles" Oral History.
6036/007. Jennie Matyas and the ILGWU: An Oral History.
6036/008. Pauline M. Newman Autobiography.
6036/009. Governor's Advisory Commission on the Cloak, Suit and Skirt Industry.
6036/010. National Coat and Suit Industry Recovery Board Records.
6036/011. Morris (Max) Sigman Criminal Case Trial.
6036/012. Abe Raskin Collection.
6036/013. Max D. Danish Collected Documents.
6036/014. "The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas" by Vanni B. Montana.
6036/015. Impartial Chairman, Decisions, Coat and Suit Industry.
6036/016. Abraham Plotkin Collection.
6036/017. Decisions of Harry Uviller, Impartial Chairman of the Board of Arbitration.
6036/018. Emil Schlessinger Collection.
6036/019. Isaac A. Hourwich Collection.
6036/020. Isidor Stenzor Collection.
6036/021. New York Coat and Suit Association Records.
6036/022. Henoch Mendelsund Interview by E. Finn.
6036/023. Jay Lovestone Interview by E. Finn.
6036/024. Maida Springer Kemp Oral History Interview.
6036/025. Connecticut Workers and Technology Project Oral History.
6036/026. George Meany Center for Labor Studies Interviews.
6036/027. Elaine Leeder "The Gentle Warrior: Rose Pesotta, Anarchist and Labor Organizer" Dissertation.
6036/028. Jay Lovestone Papers.
6036/029. "Will Herberg: From Right to Right" by Harry Ausmus.
6036/030. Lazare Teper Collection.
6036/031. International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union "Pins and Needles" Additional Scrapbooks.
6036/032. Morris Novick Papers.
6036/033. Triangle Shirt Waist Company Legal Documents.
6036/034. Mabel Durham Fuller Interview.
6036/034 OH. MabelDurham Fuller Oral History Interviews conducted by P. Sinclair.
6036/073 AV. ILGWU Related Sound Recordings.
6036/074. Joint Board Cloakmakers and Dressmakers Union and Joint Board Furriers Union Publication "Unity".
6036/075. ILG Publications.
6036/076 OH. Soyer Daniel ILGWU Heritage Project.
6036/077. Rose Newmark Collection on the ILGWU Musical “Pins and Needles”.
6036/078. Abraham Goldwasser Papers.
6036/079. Martin Morand Papers.
6036/080. Evelyn Dubrow papers.
6036/080 P. Evelyn Dubrow Photographs.
6036/081 AV. Ruth Graeber interview on "Pins and Needles".
6036/082. Jay Mazur papers.
6036/082 AV. Jay Mazur "Marching On" Audio-Visual Material.
6036/082 P. Jay Mazur Photograph Collection.
6036/083 AV. Gerald Hirschfeld "With These Hands" Audio-Visual Materials.
6036/084 P. Silvestro Ozzi Panoramic Photographs from the ILGWU's 30th and 31st Conventions.
6036/085 MB. Lois Hartel's Collection of Divina Laia's Memorabilia.
6036/086. Jay Mazur Speeches and Articles.
6036/087 P. Jay Mazur Collection of Photographs.
6036/088 P. Anna Bensh Panoramic Anniversary and Convention Photographs.
6036/089. David Dubinsky "A Mission to Histadrut in Israel".
6036/090. A Life of Her Own.
6036/091 AV. Dolores Miller ILGWU Audio-Visual Materials.
6036/091 MB. Dolores Miller ILGWU Memorabilia.
6036/091 P. Dolores Miller ILGWU Photographs.
6036/091 PUBS. Dolores Miller ILGWU and Other Publications.
6036/092 AV. Robert Adams Collection of ILGWU Audio-Visual Materials.
6036/093 P. Abe Zierlin Collection of ILGWU Convention Photographs.
6036/094 AV. Boston Workmen's Circle, Triangle Fire Centennial Show: "The Cloth From Which We Are Cut".
6036/095. Katie Quan ILGWU Papers and Publications.
6036/095 MB. Katie Quan ILGWU Memorabilia.
6036/096 MB. Bust of David Dubinsky.
6050. Newton Friedman Papers.
6100m. Herman A. Starobin Unpublished Manuscript on International Trade Regulation Policy in the United States.
6118 AV. Kheel Center AV Collection. "Clara Lemlich. Le Journal d'une meneuse de greve."
6131. Clara Lemlich Shavelson Miscellany.
6131 AV. Clara Lemlich Shavelson Audio-Visual Materials.
6131 P. Clara Lemlich Shavelson Photographs.
6159 mf. I. R. Stuart "A Study of Factors Associated with Inter-group Conflict in the Ladies' Garment Industry in New York City" on Microfilm.
6247. Lois Hartel Papers.
6247 P. Lois Hartel Photographs.
6254. Edward Stark Collection of ILGWU Papers.
6259m. Dorothy Fennell and Lois Gray. "Interview with Evelyn (Evy) Dubrow" Albany, NY, 7 Aug 2001.
6261 MB. Abraham Leibowitz Collection of ILGWU Golden Jubilee Memorabilia and Photographs.
6269. James Parton "History of the Sewing Machine" Article Reprint from Atlantic Monthly.
6299 MB: Kathy Andrade Collection of ILGWU and UNITE Quilts Memorabilia
COLLECTION DESCRIPTIONS BY SERIES
- SERIES I. CONSTITUTIONS, BY-LAWS AND CONVENTIONS, 1893-1995
  - 5780/072. Constitutions and dues books, 1893-1992., Contains constitutions, dues books, membership and strike cards of the ILGWU and some of its predecessor unions.
  - 5780/080. Convention records, 1978-1992., Contains cue cards and transcripts of the conventions of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
  - 5780/080 mf. Convention records. Microfilm, 1900-1929., Contains reports and proceedings of the conventions of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
  - 5780/193PUBS. Convention publications, 1904-1995., Consists of publications produced for the conventions of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), including Annual Journals, Reports and proceedings, General Executive Board Reports, and Financial and Statistical Reports.
- SERIES II. JOINT BOARDS, DISTRICT COUNCILS AND REGIONAL DEPARTMENTS, 1901-2000
  - Subseries A. Joint Boards, 1909-1981
    - 5780/046. Los Angeles Joint Board records, 1934-1975., Collection consists of the meeting minutes of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Los Angeles Cloak Joint Board, 1934-1968. Also included are weekly reports for the years 1941-1942.
    - 5780/046 P. Los Angeles Joint Board photographs, 1940-1975., Consists of photographs transferred from the records of the Los Angeles Cloak Joint Board. Photographs include ILGWU members, officers, and events.
    - 5780/065. San Francisco Joint Board records, 1930-1969., Contains general correspondence, questionnaires, agreements, and meeting minutes of the San Francisco Joint Board and several local unions.